And welcome back to us continuing our journey through the model class in Hugging Face Transformers library.
다시 오신 걸 환영합니다 얼굴 포옹 트랜스포머 라이브러리 모델 수업에 잘 오셨어요
We were just looking at the architecture of the llama model that you get when you simply write it,
라마 모델의 구조를 살펴보고 있었어요 단순히 작성했을 때 얻게 되는 거죠 그리고 다른
and saying that you should look at it for the others.
것들을 위해 그걸 살펴보라고 했어요
One other thing to point out is to always look at the dimensionality.
또 하나 지적할 점은 입체감을 봐야 한다는 거예요
As I briefly mentioned, look at the number of input dimensions representing the vocab, and see that
간단히 말씀드렸듯이 단어 사용을 나타내는 입력 크기 수를
that matches the output down here.
보세요 아래의 출력과 일치하죠
And you can follow the dimensions through the architecture and get a sense of what's going on.
get-ture 구조를 통해 크기를 따라가면 어떤 상황인지 알 수 있죠
All right.
좋아요
But now that we have done all of this and we've talked through what's going on and we've built our inputs,
이제 이 모든 걸 끝냈고 어떻게 되는지에 대해 얘기했고 입력을 빌드했어요
it is time for business.
이제 일할 시간이에요
This is the method model dot generate.
이건 메서드 모델 .생성이에요
It takes our inputs which are sitting on our GPU, ready for this.
이걸 위해 GPU 위에 있는 입력값을 가져가죠
Um, and we can say we want up to 80 new tokens.
새 토큰을 80개까지 원한다고 할 수 있어요
Um, a reminder, in case you forgot that what we asked for was a joke.
우리가 부탁한 건 농담이란 걸 잊으셨나 봐요
A joke for a room of data scientists.
데이터 과학자들에겐 농담거리였죠
Our favorite little experiment.
우리가 좋아하는 실험이죠
Uh, and then we take the the outputs.
그런 다음 출력부를 찍어요
We take the the first in the list of outputs, there will only be one.
첫 번째 출력물을 가져가면 하나밖에 안 남아요
Um, and we then call tokenizer dot decode to turn it from tokens back into letters to text again.
그런 다음 토큰라이저 .디코드를 호출해 토큰에서 다시 글자로 텍스트로 바꾸죠
And we print the result.
결과를 프린트하죠
Let's do it.
시작하죠
So it starts to run.
달리기 시작하네요
I like to to watch what's going on by looking down here and seeing it do a forward pass.
아래를 보면서 진행 상황을 보고 싶어요 앞으로 패스하는 걸 보는 거죠
And there comes our answer to a lighthearted joke.
명랑한 농담에 대한 답이 나왔네요
Why did the regression model break up with the neural network?
왜 회귀 모형이 신경망과 분리된 거죠?
Because it was a bad fit and the neural network was overfitting its emotions.
안 맞았거든요 신경망이 감정에 너무 부합했어요
Ah, you know, it's okay.
뭐, 괜찮아요
It's not terrible.
나쁘지 않아요
It's, uh.
네
Yeah, it's it's a perfectly plausible joke.
네, 완벽하게 그럴듯한 농담이죠
It's not the funniest that I've heard, but it's, uh.
그렇게 웃기진 않지만 뭐, 그렇죠
It's not bad.
나쁘지 않네요
Why did the logistic regression model go to therapy?
왜 물리적 회귀 모델이 상담을 받으러 갔죠?
Because it was struggling to classify its emotions.
감정을 분류하는 게 어려웠거든요
I think that's really good, actually.
정말 좋은 것 같아요
I think that's great.
좋은 것 같아요
It's simpler and it's, uh, spot on for a data science audience.
데이터 과학을 좋아하는 사람들에겐 더 간단하고 딱 맞죠
I think that's a better gag than, uh, than some of the ones at the frontier models came up with.
프론티어 모델에서 만든 것보다 더 괜찮은 개그 같아요
Uh, so good job.
정말 잘했어요
Llama 3.1.
라마 3요 1번요
Uh, the thing to bear in mind again, of course, is that we're dealing here with the 8 billion parameter
다시 한 번 명심해야 할 것은 우리가 다루는 건 80억
version of llama 3.1, the smallest version of it, and we've quantized it down to four bits, and then
개의 라마 3 매개 변수 버전이란 거예요 첫째, 가장 작은 버전이죠 4개로 퀀타이즈한 다음 두
we double quantized it.
배로 퀀타이즈했어요
Uh, so it's a this super slim version of the model, and it just told a perfectly respectable joke.
모델의 아주 날씬한 버전인데 아주 괜찮은 농담을 하더군요
Uh, so I hope you enjoyed that.
재밌게 보셨길 바라요
The next thing we do is we do some cleanup to free up some memory.
다음으로 할 일은 청소해서 메모리를 확보하는 거예요
Otherwise, if we keep running, different models will very quickly run out of GPU.
그렇지 않으면 계속 실행하면 다른 모델들이 GPU 소진으로 빠르게 소진되죠
You may find this happens to you, in which case you can always restart your session by going runtime
이런 경우에 여러분은 언제든 세션을 다시 시작할 수 있습니다 런타임 리스타트
restart session and then continue from where you left off after doing the, uh, the imports.
세션으로요 그런 다음 가져오기 다음에 중단한 곳에서 계속하죠
So the next thing I'm going to do is take everything we've just done and package it up into a nice little
다음으로 할 일은 우리가 한 모든 걸 패키지화해 작은 함수로
function that does all of it.
만드는 거예요
The function will take the name of a model and messages a usual list of dictionaries.
이 함수는 모델의 이름과 일반적인 사전 목록의 메시지를 취하죠
And let's just go through this line by line as a way of revising what we just did.
한 줄씩 살펴보면서 방금 한 걸 다시 검토해보죠
We start by using the auto tokenizer class to create a new tokenizer based on the model that we're working
오토 토큰라이저 클래스를 이용해 우리가 작업하는 모델에 기반을 둔 새 토큰라이저를 만드는 것으로 시작하죠
This line is the thing that sets the padding token to be the same as the end of sentence token.
이 선은 안쪽 토큰을 문장 토큰과 동일하게 설정하는 부분이죠
This sort of standard boilerplate thing to do.
이건 표준 절차예요
And then this.
그리고 이거요
We know and know it well.
잘 알고 있어요
This is where we apply the chat template that's suitable for this tokenizer to the messages the list.
여기서 토큰라이저에 적합한 채팅 템플릿을 리스트에 적용해요
And it will return back a series of tokens.
그럼 일련의 패를 반환하죠
We then put that onto the GPU and that we assign to inputs.
그런 다음 GPU에 넣고 입력을 할당하죠
This is new.
새롭네요
So just as another little little skill to add I'm going to say let's stream back the results.
추가할 또 다른 기술로 결과를 스트리밍으로 보여드리죠
And the Huggingface library supports that as well.
허깅페이스 라이브러리도 그걸 지원하죠
You do you create this thing called a text streamer.
텍스트 스트리머라는 걸 만들어요
You need to give it the tokenizer because as it streams back tokens, it's going to need to convert
토큰라이저를 줘야 합니다 토큰을 스트리밍하면 토큰을 텍스트로 다시
them back into, into text.
변환해야 하니까요
Uh, so it needs to know what tokenizer you're using.
어떤 토큰라이저를 쓰는지 알아야 해요
So you provide that and then action.
그걸 제공하고 액션을 하는 거죠
Uh, we first of all get the model.
먼저 모형을 get 해요
This is auto model for causal lm.
인과관계 lm 오토 모델이에요
This is the equivalent to the auto tokenizer.
오토 토큰마이저와 같은 거예요
But to load the model we say from pre-trained, we tell it the name of the model.
하지만 미리 훈련된 모델을 로드하려면 모델 이름을 말해야 해요
We say device map is auto, meaning user GPU.
장치 맵은 자동입니다 사용자 GPU 말이에요
If you've got one and we pass in our quant config that we set way up there somewhere, uh, to be four
하나를 갖고 계시면 저 위에 설치한 퀀트 구성을 넘겨요 4비트 이중
bit double quantized NF for uh, type of four bit numbers.
퀀트화된 NF로 4비트 숫자 유형을 뜻하죠
And the bfloat16 is the calculation, uh data type.
bfloat16은 데이터 타입을 계산한 거고요
And it's now time for business model dot generate.
이제 비즈니스 모델 생성 차례죠
That's the big method.
그게 큰 방법이죠
And we pass in the inputs we'll generate up to 80 new tokens and we'll give it our streamer.
새 토큰 80개까지 생성할 입력을 전달하고 스트리머를 주는 거죠
That's this is the piece that means that it will then stream the output and then we'll do our cleanup.
이게 결과물을 스트림으로 내보낸다는 뜻입니다 그런 다음 정리를 하죠
So that is the function which kind of wraps everything that we did before, but also adds in streaming.
이 함수는 우리가 전에 했던 모든 걸 래핑해주고 스트리밍도 추가해줘요
And with that, let's quite simply call Phi three with our messages, uh, using the function we just
이제 간단하게 메시지를 파이 3으로 불러볼게요 방금 만든 함수를 사용해서요
So Phi three will now load in again.
피 3은 다시 로드할게요
This will take a little bit longer for you because you will, uh, be loading it for the first time.
이건 시간이 좀 걸릴 거예요 처음으로 비트를 싣는 거니까요
Uh, I have already loaded it, so it's cached on disk.
이미 로드했어요 디스크에 캐시돼 있죠
Uh, so it doesn't need to redownload the whole thing from hugging faces.
얼굴 껴안는 걸 다시 할 필요는 없어요
Hub.
허브요
Um, there's still a little bit to do to load it in while it's doing that.
비트를 싣는 동안 할 일이 좀 더 남았어요
We could, uh.
그럴까요?
Oh, I was going to say we could look at the resources, but I think it's going to be so quick that
리소스를 살펴보자고 하려고 했는데 너무 빨리 끝날 것 같네요 스트리밍하는
I want you to see it streaming back.
걸 보여드리고 싶어요
And I think, uh, I should prepare you for the fact that you may be disappointed.
실망하실지도 모른다는 걸 미리 알려드려야 할 것 같아서요
Um, so I found that from using at least the prompt that I've got there, I was not able to get Phi
그래서 적어도 제가 갖고 있는 프롬프트만 사용해봐도 파이 3이 농담을 하게 만들 수 없다는 걸 알게 됐죠.
three to tell a joke.
Get it.
Rather, it gives some sort of general stuff that a data scientist might be talking about and sort of
데이터 과학자들이 장황하게 늘어놓는 일반적인 정보를
rambles away.
제공하죠
Now, I don't know whether I can improve the prompt to be something that's a bit more assertive for
비트 부분을 53번에게 좀 더 단호하게 바꿀 수 있을지
53, or whether it's simply not something that 53 is willing to do.
53번이 원하지 않을지는 모르겠어요
53 will do a lot of things very admirably indeed, but not this particular task.
53 소방대는 많은 일을 훌륭히 해내겠지만 이 작업은 아니에요
So I also leave that as an exercise for you as as well as trying some other models.
다른 모델과 마찬가지로 여러분도 연습해 보세요
Also see whether you can improve the prompting to get 53 to tell a joke or if it's not a jokester,
또한 수정 헌정으로 53이 농담을 하게 할 수 있는지 혹은 53이 농담이 안 웃기면 get이 잘하는
you can find some of the things it's good at.
걸 찾을 수 있는지도요
It will answer some of the other questions that we've asked llms about things like use of Llms very
우리가 llms에 대해 했던 질문에 대한 답변이 될 겁니다. Lllms의 사용에
well indeed.
대해서요.
Um, so that is the the 53 outcome.
이게 53번 결과예요
Now let's see how Gemma does.
제마는 어떤지 보죠
So the same approach, we can use our utility function for Info Google's Gemma two model, and it's
같은 접근법으로 인포 구글의 젬마 2 모델에 유틸리티 함수를 쓸 수 있어요 젬마는 시스템 프롬프트를
worth noting that Gemma doesn't support a system prompt, so you have to just pass in the user prompt
지원하지 않죠 그래서 이렇게 사용자 프롬프트를 입력해야 해요 시스템 프롬프트는
like this, which is fine because the system prompt didn't say anything special anyway.
특별한 걸 말하지 않으니 괜찮아요
And let's give Gemma a whirl.
제마를 한번 보죠
It is, of course, a 2 billion model.
물론 20억 개 모델이죠
It's a very small model.
아주 작은 모델이죠
In addition to being a very small model, we are also quantizing it down to four bits and then quantizing
아주 작은 모델일 뿐 아니라 4비트로 수량화하고 다시 수량화하고
it again.
있어요
So we are really, uh, dealing with a very slim model at this point, which shouldn't use up much memory
이 시점에서 우린 아주 슬림 모델을 다루고 있어요 메모리를 많이 쓰지 않고 잘
and also should load nice and quickly and tell a joke quickly.
로드되고 빨리 농담도 할 수 있죠
And there is its joke.
농담도 나오네요
Why did the data scientists break up with the statistician?
데이터 과학자들은 왜 통계 전문가와 헤어졌을까요?
Because they had too many disagreements about the p value.
p 값에 대한 의견이 너무 많이 충돌했거든요
It's, uh, another nerdy joke about p value.
p 값에 관한 또 다른 샌님 농담이죠
I don't get it.
Get it, get it, get it! 이해가 안 돼요
But maybe there's something obvious that I'm missing.
하지만 제가 놓치고 있는 게 있을지도 몰라요
Uh, welcome.
어서 오세요
Anyone to tell me if it is.
누가 좀 알려줘요
Uh.
네
But still, I like the way it's nice and friendly.
그래도 착하고 친근해서 좋아요
It's got another.
또 있어요
Let me know if you'd like to hear another joke.
다른 농담 듣고 싶으면 말해요
Uh, maybe when you run this, you're going to get a better joke, I don't know.
Get it로 하면 더 재밌는 농담이 나올지도 모르겠네요
Uh, but, uh, it's certainly, uh, an enjoyable, uh, tone.
하지만 확실히 즐거운 어조예요
And I think that that, uh, Gemma two has done a laudable job of, uh, certainly it's data science
2번 제마는 칭찬받을 만한 일을 했어요 데이터 과학과 관련이
relevant.
있죠
Um, and, uh, particularly when you remember that this is a tiny model that we are further quantizing.
특히 이건 작은 모델이라 수량화하고 있다는 걸 기억하면요
I think it's a fine showing from Gemma two, but certainly I fully expect when you use quantum, which
2번도 잘 보여 줬지만 제가 사용한 양자 원리를 사용하면 우수한
I have used uh, that you'll see, uh, superior results and, uh, you maybe you'll get something better
결과가 나올 거예요 3번 파이에서도 더 나은 결과가 나올 수 있겠죠
And then whatever, whether you pick the mixed trial model or something a bit slimmer that you can also
혼합 트라이얼 모델이든 좀 더 날씬한 비트 모델이든 좋은 결과가
use, I imagine you'll be able to get some good results.
나올 거예요 get it get it
You could also try asking maths questions, something which they can struggle with.
수학 문제를 내도 돼요 애들이 어려워하는 문제요
If you're dealing with difficult maths.
어려운 수학 문제라면요
But I tried asking a fairly difficult question to llama 3.1 earlier, and it had no difficulties at
하지만 라마 3에 꽤 어려운 질문을 했어요 당신도 같은 경험을 할 수 있는지
all to see if you can have the same experience.
보는 데 전혀 어려움이 없었죠
Regardless, now is a moment for you to explore using these models, trying out different things.
어쨌든 이 모델들을 사용해 보고 다양한 것을 시도해 볼 기회예요
You're working with open source models.
오픈 소스 모델로 작업하고 있죠
There's no API cost going on.
API 비용은 없어요
The only cost you you pay is if you're using up.
모든 걸 소진할 때만 대가를 치르죠
If you're not using Free Colab, but you're using up some of your, uh, units from the, uh, the Google
프리 콜랍을 안 쓰는데 구글 콜랍 비용으로 단위를 쓴다면
Colab, uh, costs.
말이죠
Um, the I'm using 1.76 units per hour.
1을 쓰고 있어요 시간당 76유닛요
So there's really plenty of time to be, uh, to be working with this and enjoying inference on open
이와 함께 작업할 시간은 충분합니다 포옹하는 트랜스포머 라이브러리를 이용해
source models using the hugging face Transformers library.
오픈 소스 모델 추론을 즐길 수 있죠